Guide to the Michael K. Honey Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Michael K. Honey Papers
1908-2005
1976-2005
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections
5294
Honey, Michael K.
18.19 cubic ft. 18 boxes
Professor of labor and ethnic studies and American history at the University of Washington, Tacoma.
Michael Honey received his Ph.D. in history from Northern Illinois University in 1988 and an MA in history from Howard University in 1978. He taught at University of Maryland, Wesleyan University, and University of Puget Sound, taking a post-doc at the Stanford Humanities Center in 1989. In 1990 he became a founding faculty of the University of Washington, Tacoma, helping to devise the curriculum for the Interdisciplinary Arts and Sciences Program (now a School of UWT). He initiated and taught the first black history and labor history courses; and with Kathie Friedman Kasaba, a sociologist, he designed the Ethnic, Gender and Labor Studies curriculum (now a major in IAS). Honey initiated the Ernie Tanner Labor and Ethnic Studies Center and worked closely with ILWU Local 23 and with African American churches in developing public programs in the community on labor and black freedom movement studies. He worked closely with the National Civil Rights Museum in Memphis and continued his links to organizing and research in the South, where he had been the southern director of a civil liberties organization before going to graduate school. He held the Harry Bridges Endowed Chair of Labor Studies, 2000-2004; later became a vice-president and president of the Labor and Working-Class History Association; and has continued to work with the Pacific Northwest Labor History Association since he came to Tacoma. Honey received awards from the Guggenheim Foundation, the National Endowment for the Humanities, and other grants for his labor and civil rights and Martin Luther King studies, and book awards from the Robert F. Kennedy Foundation, the Organization of American Historians, the Southern Historical Association, the State of Washington and the United Association of Labor Educators for his four monographs in labor and civil rights history and his edited volume of King’s labor speeches. His files include numerous oral histories, research in southern labor and African American history and music, teaching materials, and documents of his professional growth as a historian with wide national recognition and as a faculty member at the University of Washington, and as the Fred and Dorothy Haley endowed Professor of Humanities at the UW Tacoma.
Organized into 2 accessions.
Accession No. 5294-001, Michael K. Honey papers, 1976-2001
Accession No. 5294-002, Michael K. Honey papers, 1977-2005
General correspondence, research files, articles, student records, subject files, conference files, program files, pamphlets, video recordings, audio cassette recordings.
Research files contain copies of correspondence held at other institutions concerning labor efforts in Alaska during the first half of the century and southern unionists in North Carolina during the Civil War.
Research materials for Honey's work on the Civil Rights movement and labor activism in the American South, materials on labor organizing and civil rights in the Pacific Northwest, oral recordings of black labor activists, and chattel slavery. Contains slides, newspaper clippings, videocassettes and sound cassettes of the aforementioned subjects as well as his program 'Links on the Chain.''
Open to all users, but access to portions of the papers restricted. Contact repository for details.
Honey, Michael K.$vArchives; University of Washington, Tacoma; University of Washington, Tacoma.$bInterdisciplinary Arts and Sciences; University of Washington.$bUniversity Archives; College teachers$zWashington (State)$zTacoma$vArchives; Historians$zWashington (State)$zTacoma$vArchives; Labor movement$xStudy and teaching (Higher)$zWashington (State)$zTacoma; Labor movement$xHistory$zUnited States; Labor movement$xResearch$zUnited States; Sound recordings; Video recordings; University Archives/Faculty Papers; Colleges and Universities; Washington (State); Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Alaska; Labor History
- Michael K. Honey papers, 1908-2001; 5294-001; 8.00 cu. ft. (8 boxes)
  General correspondence, research files, articles, student records, subject files, conference files, program files, pamphlets, video recordings, audio cassette recordings; 1908-2001 (bulk 1976-2001). Research files contain copies of correspondence held at other institutions concerning labor efforts in Alaska during the first half of the century and southern unionists in North Carolina during the Civil War.
  Open to all users, but access to portions of the papers restricted. Contact repository for details.
  Bibliographic Source: Michael Honey¶ Donor Database Source: Michael Honey
  - Alaska Labor, 1935-1955; 0.2 cubic ft. (Box 1)
  - North Carolina Unionists Civil War Research, 1985-1986; 0.8 cubic ft. (Box 1)
  - UW-Tacoma/Interdisciplinary Arts and Sciences, 1990-2000; 1 cubic ft. (Box 2)
  - Marxist and New Left Pamphlets, 1960s-1970s; 1 cubic ft. (Box 3)
  - Conference Papers, 1982-2000; 0.25 cubic ft. (Box 4)
  - Articles, 1981-1989; 0.25 cubic ft. (Box 4)
  - Center for the Study of Community and Society (CSCS) Admin., 1991-2000; 0.3 cubic ft. (Box 4)
  - Ernie Tanner Center (ETC) Admin., 1995-1997; 0.2 cubic ft. (Box 4)
  - Martin Luther King Jr. Institute, 1990-1997; 0.3 cubic ft. (Box 5)
  - "Links on the Chains" Files, 1985-1997; 0.9 cubic ft. (Box 5-6)
  - Programs at UW-Tacoma, 1991-2000; 0.3 cubic ft. (Box 6)
  - Southern Labor and Black Civil Rights, 1988-1993; 0.2 cubic ft. (Box 6)
  - Course Evaluations and Tests, 1984-1989; 0.3 cubic ft. (Box 6-7)
  - Northern Illinois University, 1978-1981; 0.4 cubic ft. (Box 7)
  - Howard University, 1976-1978; 0.4 cubic ft. (Box 7)
  - VHS and Cassette Tapes, 1988-2001; 0.4 cubic ft. (Box 7-8)
  - Job Applications, 1984-1990; 0.2 cubic ft. (Box 8)
  - Graduate School Items, 1980-1988; 0.2 cubic ft. (Box 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1978-1996; 0.4 cubic ft. (Box 8)
- Michael K. Honey papers, 1977-2005; 5294-002; 10.19 cubic feet (10 boxes)
  Research materials for Honey's work on the Civil Rights movement and labor activism in the American South, materials on labor organizing and civil rights in the Pacific Northwest, oral recordings of black labor activists and chattel slavery. Contains slides, newspaper clippings, VHS and record tapes of the aforementioned subjects as well as his program 'Links on the Chain.'
  No restrictions on access.
  Donated by Michael K. Honey, 2019-06-07
  - Organizing the South - Racial Problem, Undated (Box 1)
  - Racism and United Packinghouse Workers of America (UPWA) Background, and Fair Employment Practice Committee, Undated (Box 1)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Notes, Undated (Box 1)
  - Anti-Communism, Undated (Box 1)
  - Memphis Left, Undated (Box 1)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Red Scare, 1994; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mill, Mine, and Smelter Workers (MMSW) Tennessee, 2005 (Box 1)
  - McGurty Interview, Undated (Box 1)
  - Communist Party (CP), Undated (Box 1)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Anti-Discrimination, 1994; 3 folders (Box 1)
    Includes Masters thesis
  - United Packinghouse Workers of America (UPWA) Anti-Discrimination, Undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - United Packinghouse Workers of America (UPWA) Notes, 1992; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Crossroads: Social Relations, Economies, and Communities in the South Sound and Beyond, 2003 (Box 2)
    Textbook
  - Center for AOC Studies, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Rebecca Mckinley - Transcript, Undated (Box 2)
  - Firestone Workers - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Hosea Hudson - Transcript, 1985 (Box 2)
  - George King - Transcript, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Hilly Pride - Transcript, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Taylor Rogers - Interview and Notes, 1996 (Box 2)
  - James Robinson - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Lonnie Rowland - Transcript, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Susie Wade - Transcript, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Buckeye Local, George Isabele, Undated (Box 2)
  - William Glover, Fannie Henderson, and Thomas Watkinz Affidavits, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Bill Lucy - Transcript, 1990; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Leroy Boyd - Transcript, 1989-2004 (Box 2)
  - Webb-Miller Case, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Evelyn Bates - Revision, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Evelyn Bates - Transcript, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Le Roy Boyd from Ortiz, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Irene Branch - Revision, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Irene Branch - Transcript, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Alzada Clark - Transcript, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Leroy Clark - Transcript, Undated (Box 2)
  - Clarence Coe - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Clarence Coe - Revision, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Clarence Coe - Original Interview Format, 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Matthew Davis - Revised, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Matthew Davis and Edward Harrell - Transcripts, 1984-1995 (Box 2)
  - George Holloway Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2)
  - George Holloway, 1990 (Box 2)
  - George Isabele - Transcript, Undated (Box 2)
  - George Holloway - Revised, 1990-1995 (Box 2)
  - George Holloway - Transcript, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Ida Leachman - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Edward Lindsay - Transcript, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Hilly and Laura Pride, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Bill Lucy - Transcript, Undated (Box 2)
  - Labor Union Card Notes 1, Undated (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights Book Citations, Undated (Box 3)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Split, Undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Racial Politics, Undated (Box 3)
  - United Packinghouse Workers of America (UPWA), Undated (Box 3)
  - Historians - Post War Period, Undated (Box 3)
  - Willie McGee, Undated (Box 3)
  - Historians: Labor Red Scare, Undated (Box 3)
  - Highlander File, Undated (Box 3)
  - United Packinghouse Workers (UPWA) + Red Baiting Attacks, Undated (Box 3)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Accommodates, 1951-1955 So Does the Ruling Class, Undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Labor/Civil Rights Theme, Undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Wilmington, Undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1946-1953 South, Undated (Box 3)
  - Brotherhood of Railway Trainmen: Black Exclusion 1850s-1929, Undated (Box 3)
  - Racial Tension, Undated (Box 3)
  - National Recovery Administration (NRA) Black Workers 1933-1936, Undated (Box 3)
  - Historians: Labor; World War II, Undated (Box 3)
  - Historians: Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) + Historians on the Communist Party, Undated (Box 3)
  - Labor Union Card Notes 2, Undated (Box 3)
  - 1940-1941 Memphis, Undated (Box 3)
  - Southern Conference Educational Fund (SCEF)/Bradens, Undated (Box 3)
  - The Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) and Civil Rights in the South, Undated (Box 3)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), Undated (Box 3)
  - The American Federation of Labor (AFL) - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Merger, Undated (Box 3)
  - Statistics, Undated (Box 3)
  - Antebellum Memphis, Undated (Box 3)
  - New South, 1860-1900, Undated (Box 4)
  - Early Memphis Unions, Undated (Box 4)
  - Rise of Segregation and Lynch Law, Undated (Box 4)
  - Segregation System, Undated (Box 4)
  - Unions and Segregation: The American Federation of Labor (AFL) 1900-1929, Undated (Box 4)
  - Biographies, Undated (Box 4)
  - The Repression, Undated (Box 4)
  - The Crump System, Undated (Box 4)
  - Industrialization, Undated (Box 4)
  - 1930s The American Federation of Labor (AFL), Undated (Box 4)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) In Memphis 1936-1937, Undated (Box 4)
  - 1939 River Strike, Undated (Box 4)
  - Pre World War II Red Scare, Undated (Box 4)
  - Media, Undated (Box 4)
  - World War II Unions, Undated; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Historical Slides, Undated (Box 4)
    Contains film slides on Black Women, Slavery, Emancipation, Industrialization, Children in Mills, 1920s-1960s, Black Soldiers in WWI and II, Chinese and Latino History, Segregation and the KKK, Northern Migration and Black Personalities.
  - Seminar Paper: Class Conflict and White Unionist Sentiment in North Carolina, 1978 (Box 4)
    Hardback book
  - Reminisces by Del Castle, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Labor's Heritage. Volume 4. Quarterly of the George Meany Memorial Archives. No. 1, 1992 (Box 4)
    Magazine
  - National Committee: For the Defense of Political Prisoners + 'MNPL 2005 751 Club' Pin, Undated (Box 4)
    Includes newspaper clipping and 'MNPL 2005 751 Club' Pin found loose in Honey's collection
  - Census of Population: 1950, Undated (Box 4)
  - J.W. Brister Library Monograph Series 6, 1982-1986 (Box 4)
  - Lawrence McGurty, Undated (Box 4)
  - Al Greenburg File 1950s (Box 4)
    Newspaper clippings
  - Lawrence McgGurty Papers, Undated (Box 4)
  - Ralph Helstein Fourth Biennial Wages Contract, Undated (Box 4)
  - 1952 Hearing and Aftermath, Scales Arrest, and Communist Party (CP) in Memphis 1952 Onwards, Undated (Box 4)
  - Racial Liberalism and Capton and Mitchell Flashcard Notes, Undated (Box 4)
  - Highlander Files, WWII, Undated (Box 4)
  - Civil Rights 1989 Onwards, Undated (Box 4)
  - Harvester Strike, Undated (Box 4)
  - Race Riots, Columbia, Tennessee 1946, Undated (Box 4)
  - Memphis "Freedom Train" 1947, Undated (Box 4)
  - Memphis Since Crump, David M. Tucker, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Memphis Urban League (MUL), LC 1944-1958, Undated (Box 5)
  - Local 19, Postwar (Box 5)
  - Local 19 1955 Onwards, 1983 (Box 5)
  - International Harvester Plant, Memphis, George Holloway, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Memphis Furniture Strike + Willie Rudd, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Economy, Undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Policy and Racism, Memphis, 1950s Onwards, Undated (Box 5)
  - 1940 Census, Population, Undated (Box 5)
  - Worker and Industry, 1930-1950, Census, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Economy, 1945-1955, Undated (Box 5)
  - War Labor Memphis Reports, Undated (Box 5)
  - Wage Rates, Undated (Box 5)
  - Labor and Race, WWII, Mayor's Files, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Economy 1946 Onwards, Undated (Box 5)
  - Political Economy, Tennessee and Memphis 1955 Onwards, Undated (Box 5)
  - 1950 Census Memphis, Undated (Box 5)
  - 1960 Census Memphis, Undated (Box 5)
  - 1970 Census Memphis, Undated (Box 5)
  - 1980 Census Memphis, Undated (Box 5)
  - 1990 Census Memphis, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Economy and Unions 1950s, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Labor Force Characteristics 1950-1970, Undated (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clips, Memphis Labor Violence 1950s Onwards, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Economy Today, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis 1970s, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis 1980s, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Poverty 1980s, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Poverty 1990s, 1992-1996 (Box 5)
  - Memphis 1990s, Undated (Box 5)
  - Matthew R. Davis and New Chicago, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Poverty, Mississippi Delta, Undated (Box 5)
  - Poverty 1968-1972, Undated (Box 5)
  - 1930 Census of Manufacture, Population, and Labor, Undated (Box 5)
  - Southern Agriculture, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Views of Memphis History and Memphis Research, Undated (Box 5)
  - Memphis Photos, Undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Crump, Undated (Box 6)
  - Memphis The American Federation of Labor (AFL), Undated (Box 6)
  - Industrialization; Union Organizing 1935-1937, Undated (Box 6)
  - Memphis: Black Workers, 1983-1989 (Box 6)
  - Memphis Economy and Conditions 1930s, Undated (Box 6)
  - Memphis: New Deal (Box 6)
  - Memphis: Civil Liberties (Box 6)
  - The Great Riverfront Strike 1939, 1985-1990 (Box 6)
  - National Maritime Union of America (NMU)/International Longshoremen's Association (ILA), Undated (Box 6)
  - United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing and Allied Workers of America (UCAPAWA) 1940s, Undated (Box 6)
  - United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing and Allied Workers of America (UCAPAWA) 1937-1942, Undated (Box 6)
  - Firestone/United Rubber Workers (URW), Undated (Box 6)
  - United Automobile Workers of America (UAW) Region 8: Past and Present, Undated (Box 6)
    Book
  - Links on the Chain Musical by Michael Honey, 1997-2001 (Box 6)
    Includes photo
  - Robert Church Jr, Undated (Box 7)
  - Secondary Work Memphis, Undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - JR Watkins/Woodworkers, Hostile Employers WWII, Cudahy WWII, Undated (Box 7)
  - Memphis Labor WWII, Undated (Box 7)
  - A. Philip Randolph Incident 1944, Undated (Box 7)
  - Fair Employment Practice Commission Act (FEPC), Undated (Box 7)
  - Firestone Workers, Undated (Box 7)
  - United Furniture Workers of America (UFWA) 1946-1955, Undated (Box 7)
  - Post WWII Unions, Undated (Box 7)
  - Local 19 1945-1955 and Buckeye Plant Strike and Purge, Undated (Box 7)
  - Memphis Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), Undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - United Furniture Workers of America (UFWA), Undated (Box 7)
  - Stetson Kennedy, Undated (Box 7)
  - Ku Klux Klan, Undated (Box 7)
  - Southern Labor Archives, Miscellaneous, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Mississippi 1946-1949, Undated (Box 7)
  - Allan Haywood Organizing Notes 1944 Onwards, Undated (Box 7)
  - Firestone Workers, Undated (Box 7)
  - Tennessee Politics, Undated (Box 7)
  - Black Workers and Postwar War, Undated (Box 7)
  - Henry Wallace, Undated (Box 7)
  - Memphis Bus and Industry Post 1945, Undated (Box 7)
  - Racist Upsurge 1980s, Undated (Box 7)
  - American Snuff Company Strike 1950, Undated (Box 7)
  - Taft-Hartley Slave Labor Act, Undated (Box 7)
  - Ed Mcrea Clippings/file, Undated (Box 7)
  - Southern States Industrial Co, Post-War and WWII Anti-Communism, Undated (Box 7)
  - Food Tobacco Agriculture Allied Workers Union of America (FTA), Undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Videocassettes, 1980-2001; 10 videocassettes (VHS) (Box 8)
    Includes: 'Pat Wright and the TEGC 2001,' 'Cleophas Williams,' 'Michael Honey,' 'Jack O'Dell Martin Luther King Class VWT 7/26/97,' 'Clayborne Canson Passages of Martin Luther King 1.51,' 'Bettie Fikes and Michael Honey April 2001 Woody Guthrie Series,' 'Bettie Fikes 5th Grade 1980 - UW Milwaukee,' Michael Honey 10/25/1999,' 'Michael Honey Lecture ETC 1/22/1990,' and 'Will You Stand?'.
  - Sound cassettes and Correspondence, 1981-2016; 59 sound cassettes; 3 sound microcassettes (Box 9)
    Includes numerous sound cassettes: 'Links on the Chain' soundtrack, and oral history tapes from the 1980s not deposited into the Southern Oral History Program. Other cassettes include: 'Black Workers Remember (Michael Honey),' 'Links on the Chain,' 'Links. Wesleyan 2/18/1988 Copy,' '2/18/1988 Wesleyan University Program Original,' 'Betty Fikes Program - AAME 2/24/1993,' and 'Links on the Chain (Selections) Mike Honey; David Sawyer 17/2/1989 Early Version.'
    Correspondence includes a letter to Conor Casey and letter from Jaycie Vos at Southern Oral History Program.
  - Links on the Chain Series 1 and Triangle Fire Slides, 1986-1996 (Box 10)
    Slides for 'Links on the Chain Series 1,' and 'Triangle Fire.'
  - Links on the Chain Series 2 Slides, 1989-1996 (Box 10)
    Slides for 'Links on the Chain Series 2' Slides
  - Photographs of the 1968 Memphis Sanitation Strike and Dr Martin Luther King Jr Slides, 2003 (Box 10)
    Includes slides for 'I am a Man' presentation of photographs of 1968 Memphis Strike and MLK
  - Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) Slides, 1977-1989 (Box 10)
    Includes slides depicting the IWW and 'Hard Hitting Songs' sheet
  - Links Slides 1, 1989-1992 (Box 10)
    Includes variety of slides on slavery and labor movements alongside a few 'Links on the Chain' slides missing from series 1 and 2
  - Links Slides 2, 1986-1992 (Box 10)
    Includes variety of slides on slavery and labor movements
  - Martin Luther King and CRM Slides, 1992 (Box 10)
    Includes variety of slides on MLK's moments movements
  - Memphis Black Workers Slides and Notes, Undated (Box 10)
    Includes slides on Memphis workers and notes on said slides
  - Parts of Links/Solidarity Slides, 1986-1989 (Box 10)
    Includes slides from 'Links on the Chain,' and images of solidarity
  - Slavery Slides, 1986-1991 (Box 10)
    Includes slides depicting the Atlantic slave trade